[Music]
Welcome to this what's new session in
Dynamics Business Central
uh
2025 way one. I'm Bardock Nuden one of
the application architects um and I'm
going to talk about concurrency in
inventory
posting and from a feature point of view
that is actually all there is to know.
So the remainder of this content is for
developers. In BC25 or earlier only one
user or session can insert into item
lure at the same time and in this case I
have started
two journal item journal postings and if
you look closer you will be able to see
that one of them is progressing and the
other is not. nothing happens on the
left right side and if you wait long
enough you may see that you get a lock
timeout. So that is in previous
versions. Now two users or many user
basically uh can insert and if you look
closer you can see that both of these
are counting and progressing. How do you
enable it? Well, we have in feature
management, we have added a new feature
key for enable multiple users to post
item ledger entries and value entries at
the same time. Basically, that's that
could be the entire
documentation. It's off by default. Um,
we will set it on by default in three
releases.
And you can also turn this on and off as
you will. There's no upgrade. there's
no no penalty to go back and forth to
try it out. And there's more because
while we were at it, we actually did it
also to the U project ledger or job
ledger as it was was called and resource
ledgers. Same rules as the others. And
which tables does this encompass? It's
um all the item ledger related tables
and there are a lot as you can see but
also as I said resource and project
entries. So how did it work in BC25 and
previously? Usually when we post
something we have two functions. We have
some kind of init function and this is
more more a general thing and then we
post or insert or whatever we call those
functions. And what we do there is we
start out with a lock table. Then we
find the last entry
which puts a semaphore lock if you will
on that
table. And from now on only you can
update the uh
ledgers. And then we take whatever entry
number that was
and save it in a counter. And whenever
we want to insert a new entry, we just
increment this counter and assign it to
the entry number. I mean you know know
all this and insert. So this is how it
was and only one user can do anything at
the same time. Now you can see in the
init some ledger the code is gone.
There's no locking here and instead of
incrementing the counter the next entry
number we just ask for the next entry
number which may not be you know 1 + 1
where we use a number sequence. And when
you think of number sequences, you can
think of bit like you know this number
dispenser that you would see at a
pharmacy or a bakery. So with this
design multiple sessions can insert at
the same time but also unused numbers
are lost just like if you decide you
don't want to wait at the
bakery. Of course um the code in some
ledger is still there because you can
turn this feature on and off. So you
will see this statement you know if
inventory setup do use leg legacy
posting that would be sprinkled around
um in code. And you might think now what
about the item register? Because
if different transactions um insert at
the same time then then what about this
from and two entry
numbers. So you can see that with the
last two uh registers we have the from
and two numbers are indeed overlapping a
lot actually both for the itemage
entries and for the value entries. So
how do we you know do a drill
down? Well, you can see that first of
all we do as we usually do. We filter on
the entry number but now we also filter
on the register number because all the
entries now have a new field called item
register number. You may also wonder why
do we say zero or 102 in this case.
That's for backwards compatibility. So
if you have old entries, item register
number won't be filled in. It'll be
zero. But then in those cases, the to
and from entry numbers are correct. I
they're always correct, but
sequential. Then we have automatic cost
posting. one of our enemies for locking
because um many users, most actually
have this flag on in inventory setup
because they want the general ledger to
reflect what they have on inventory. And
the effect is that when you post item
journals for instance, same for sales
order, purchase orders, whatever. Um, we
call out to the item journal post line
which then calls out to GL post to post
the finance. That means that immediately
you start posting an item journal, you
would also lock the GL, meaning people
cannot do payments and other GL stuff.
And of course, we do that for every
line. But so what we did did for BC26
was that we basically do the same as
before, but we postpone it till the end.
meaning that several users can do it at
the same time except they will of course
be locked for the GL part. And maybe now
is time to see it in action. See, so I
have created some item journal batches
here. There's
one. There's another.
And instead of posting, I'll just
preview because a preview post is the
same as posting all the way except that
it rolls back at the end. But as as goes
for locking, it will do the same. So if
I click preview posting
here and
here, maybe you can see it, maybe not.
But both both of them are counting now.
And at one point, one of them will get
to the GL
posting. That will happen now maybe. So
now you can see one of them is posting
to GL while the other one is waiting
because only one can still post to
GL and there the first one finished. Now
the second one can finish its job and of
course if the right one took would take
more than 30 seconds then we would get
the lock time out of course and the
other then to what about you as a
developer? So what if you are adding
entries? Um well you need to adopt to
the same patterns as we have meaning
using um the number sequences which
again is meaning get you can use the get
next entry number functions on the entry
tables and you would also need to
specify the item register number in
those entry tables at least if you want
the drill down from registers to work.
And what happens if you don't and still
turn on this feature? Well, you might
get you might get or no, you will get a
record with entry number something
already exists and then you have a call
from your
customer. However, we try to be a bit
more robust or
resilient. So before each batch, we
actually check that our number sequence
is aligned with the table. Meaning that
if you running are running some old
style code that has posted something
then we make sure that it's in sync
before we start
posting. But then there are the events
where you add entries during event
calls. So this is one of them an example
and uh you can see that in this case we
pass on the value entry number that you
are expected to increment in case you
insert uh a value entry. So to safeguard
that we save the current value entry
number and after the event we check
whether it was changed. So that function
there first it compares the value entry
number and if there's no change it'll
just
exit. Then it checks for whether this
feature is on or not and if it is it
will go and make sure that the counter
or the
um number sequence for in this case
value entry fits the table. But even so
there may be race conditions where you
know somebody has just inserted
something old style and then somebody
else runs uh the new code. And finally
does this matter? I mean how does it
perform? So basically the same scenarios
just saw but in PR with automatic cost
posting on different items so we don't
have any interference there with the
indexes and whatnot.
So if we post one batch it took you know
ballpark of 20
seconds and if we post two um batches as
we just demoed it will take in this case
23 seconds but don't put too much in the
exact into the exact
numbers. Um which gives you a gain of
2/3 in this case. Um, and remember after
one has after the both have finished
posting the inventory, they need to post
to GL one at a time. So, one will always
be slower than I mean one of them will
always have to wait for the other for
the GL. But the real gain is that the
second user isn't locked out now. You
should be able to do transfer orders and
whatnot while other people are working
with purchase orders and yeah,
stuff. That's it. Thank you.